<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>5minutes - Management</title><link href="http://5minutes.youkidea.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://5minutes.youkidea.com/feeds/management.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://5minutes.youkidea.com/</id><updated>2019-10-09T21:20:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Prepare your career path session</title><link href="http://5minutes.youkidea.com/prepare-your-career-path-session.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-09T21:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-09T21:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Romain Garrigues</name></author><id>tag:5minutes.youkidea.com,2019-10-09:/prepare-your-career-path-session.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to be prepared to have a constructive career path discussion&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, as manager we decided to do the big jump and start a career path discussion with our direct reports!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, we can roughly be in 3 situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don't know at all where they want to be in 5 years (80%),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a gist of where they are heading to (10%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a plan (10%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;They don't know&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the interesting bit, where we can add the most value.
The first step is to understand why they don't know:
They have never thought about it before (that raises an important point: before initiating a career discussion, some time should be allowed for the person to think about it. There is no way that somebody will come with a relevant plan on the fly),
They have thought about it, but it's so hard that they didn't progress much,
They don't believe that's possible to have an interesting discussion about this topic, too many uncertainties in life (in this case you have to convince them to at least give it a try with you and see how it goes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on their current experience, the discussion will be different (see the different guides for more details).
A really good source of insight is any job board. What better than the market can give you what the market wants?
As a well known fact, most of the job ads are "profiles" descriptions more than positions in a given company. That makes these ads even more useful to understand what is expected for a given "general" role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3 main steps to define these archetypes of roles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find job title patterns in your industry (for tech people in the web industry, that would be CTO, VP of Engineering, Chief of Staff, Principal Engineer, Architect, Expert,...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each archetype, identify the description of their mission. That would allow us to project ourselves in the future and give us a flavour of our daily tasks. It could immediately raise red flags (VP of Engineer involves people management, and you would like to stay 100% technical for example)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each archetype, gather the requirements listed, which would be essential to plan what should be the next next in people's career to go towards this goal (it will be complicated to switch to VP of Engineering straight away from an IC - Individual Contributor - role, as you don't have management experience. It could then orient you to help them starting their management experience by having one direct report, then 2, then a team, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also try to match these archetypes with personality tests (I really like the one from &lt;a href="https://www.16personalities.com/"&gt;16personalities.com&lt;/a&gt; to help orient the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these archetypes, ask them to choose one or two maximum. Their favorite(s) one(s), or their less worse ones, if really undecided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you need to think about which area they should focus on to achieve their goal.
It could either be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something that they would like to focus on first,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something easily achievable on your current company structure,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something you have experience with and will be able to provide them a great support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally this plan will be part of their quarterly objectives, which means that you allow them to spend some time on it outside of their usual duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;They have a gist of it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process used above is still valid. You can just already scrap the parts that have already being identified as not motivating for them and spend more time coming with a plan.
I think that's still worth going through the unwanted roles if they don't have strong arguments justifying what they don't like. That could wrongly come:
A lack of knowledge on what these roles entail (being a manager? Will I continue to code? Not ready to stop it!),
An evolving domain (managing people now has different challenges than 10 years ago, technical challenges are also vastly different)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;They know&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, that would be more useful to directly concentrate on what they want to achieve.
If they are already that self-driven, you can ask them what was their plan in your company? In general?
From there, you can support them as much as you can in the direction they want to head towards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Career"></category><category term="Management"></category><category term="Coaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Why should we talk about career path</title><link href="http://5minutes.youkidea.com/why-should-we-talk-about-career-path.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-09T12:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-09T12:36:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Romain Garrigues</name></author><id>tag:5minutes.youkidea.com,2019-10-09:/why-should-we-talk-about-career-path.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why should we talk about career path&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Did you already wonder where will you be in 5 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, you may have been asked this question during a job interview, isn't it?
And honestly, 95% of the people will have the same answer "I don't know, that's so far away. I'm not even sure about where I will be in 3 months". Or they will try to find an answer to please the person that asked the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a manager, I consider as one of my duties to help my reports to grow from a career point of view. I integrated career discussions during our official quarterly reviews, and I was not surprised about the answers I had during our first session on this topic: "I don't know"...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are people usually not knowing? Because that's hard. Really hard.
It depends on your next project(s), your next promotion, the evolution of your team in the company, the market (if you want to change your job), the way other companies work, etc.
There are a lot of reasons to show that any plan you can come with will be highly inaccurate.
But should we not try anything because it's too hard? Or because we won't have it right? Should we not play a match against a stronger opponent "on paper"?
Is it then a lost cause, a completely useless exercise ? I don't think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As people usually just run with the flow, they start with the first project assigned to them when they join a new company (frequently a non-critical / non-interesting one, as they first need to build their trust in you). Then they jump to the next project, usually decided for them by the management. Then next one, etc. Until they consider that they are not growing anymore (various reasons: no perspective of technical evolution, or hierarchical progression, or pay increase, or &lt;put_reason_here&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when you reach that stage, you look for the next step (= job) with the career path you have built passively over the last X years.
Depending on how lucky they have been, they will be able to access (or not) the next "dream position of the moment".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where you can act right now! Instead of waiting for things to happen, start thinking about it way more seriously!! What are the different positions existing in your domain? How can you already anticipate some of your moves to be in a better position for the future?
You want to manage big teams in the future? Few chances that it will happen if you don't start managing 1-2 people first.
You want to work for company Y? What are the technologies they are using? Their culture? The challenges they are currently facing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's be clear here: I'm not talking about a bullet-proof method to have 100% chances to get to your dream job in X years, but to increase your chances. To be prepared in the right way. To have a solid story to tell about when you describe what drives you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You remember, I told you that I initiated this discussion with my reports during quarterly reviews. That were the most productive sessions I ever had with them, by far (more about these sessions &lt;here&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The different guides&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what you may find of interest depending on your situation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a junior and just started working: the junior guide (in progress),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are mid-level developer and start noticing that you learn less these days in your company: the mid-level challenges (in progress),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are senior and currently really passive in your career: the full career guide (in progress),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a manager and would like to help your reports to have a career plan: the &lt;a href="http://5minutes.youkidea.com/prepare-your-career-path-session.html"&gt;career path session preparation&lt;/a&gt; and the career path session example (in progress),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a developer that starts having more of a tech lead role, as well as new management duties: the should-I-be-a-manager guide (in progress).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Career"></category><category term="Management"></category><category term="Coaching"></category></entry></feed>